Guide to the Maurice Forge Papers WAG.106
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Maurice Forge Papers
1936-1986
1940-1950
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Forge, Maurice, 1902-1990
WAG.106
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton.
Maurice Forge (1902-1990) was a New York bus driver who became an organizer, news editor, and ultimately a vice president of the Transport Workers Union (TWU). In the late 1930s, Forge began organizing the TWU's Airline Transport Division (ATD). A decade later, a union-wide effort to sever TWU ties with the Communist Party resulted in Forge's expulsion from the TWU. The Maurice Forge Papers include materials from Forge's TWU career, including union publicity materials, official correspondence, and transcripts of Forge's TWU hearing and of the government deportation hearing of TWU official John Santo.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Maurice Forge, 1986. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1986.011 and 1986.025.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Maurice Forge was born on October 6, 1902 in New York City. After losing his job as a commercial artist in 1930, Forge became a bus driver. Working at night, Forge began organizing by day for the fledgling Transport Workers Union (TWU). His union involvement deepened when he became editor of the TWU Bulletin. Forge, a Communist Party member, was hired as a full-time paid union organizer, and became the leading force behind the TWU's Publicity Department. In the late 1930s, Forge became a TWU vice-president and director of the union's new Air Transport Division (ATD). Airline organizing brought him into conflict with other CIO unions, as well as with powerful elements within the TWU who questioned the wisdom of investing union resources in this new venture. Despite some successes, Forge was discouraged about the lack of adequate support from the TWU establishment, leading him to champion the formation of a Committee for Air Transport Autonomy (CATA) after TWU's Biennial Convention in 1948. In the late 1940s, TWU president Michael Quill broke with the Communist Party, and union officials set about severing TWU's ties to the Party. Forge was tried before a union committee and, along with other influential TWU members, expelled from the union.
Forge went back to bus driving on Long Island, and continued to participate, unofficially, in the activities of TWU Local 252. Eventually he bought and ran the Crestwood Bus Company (he sold the company in 1970). Over the years, Forge maintained contact with many former colleagues from the ATD and from TWU Locals 100 and 252. He also remained close to Michael Quill, and, after many years lobbying to regain his TWU membership, Forge was granted reinstatement in 1984.
Forge died in Freeport, Long Island in February 1990.
Scope and Content Note
The Maurice Forge Papers include materials from Forge's TWU career, including union publicity materials, official correspondence, and transcripts of Forge's TWU hearing and of the government deportation hearing of TWU official John Santo.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged chronologically. Series II is arranged alphabetically according to type of material; within these sections files are arranged chronologically.
Organized into two series:
Missing Title
General Files
Clippings, Credentials, Flyers, Pamphlets, Photographs
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
For more information about the Transport Workers Union of America, see the Transport Workers Union of America Records (WAG 235).
The Transport Workers Union Oral History Collection (OH 11) includes an interview with Maurice Forge.
Separated Material
TWU newspapers, Transport Workers Bulletin, Rank and File Newsletter and the Transit Bulletin were transferred to the Tamiment Library newspaper collection.
Correspondence.; Articles.; Labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York.; Collective labor agreements |x Transport workers |z United States.; Transport workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York |x History.; Transport workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Airlines |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Hearings (event); Bus drivers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Reports.; Airlines |x Employees |z United States.; Communists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Minutes (administrative records); Collective bargaining |x Transport workers |z United States.; Collective bargaining -- United States.; Leaflets (printed works); Santo, John, 1908-; Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Company; Forge, Maurice, 1902-1990; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100; Transport Workers Union of America. Air Transport Division; Committee for Air Transport Autonomy; Transport Workers Union of America; Trans World Airlines; Interborough Rapid Transit Company; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 252 (Westbury, N.Y.); Transport Workers Union of America. Local 234 (Philadelphia, Pa.); Pan American Airways Corporation; Quill, Mike.; Forge, Maurice, 1902-1990
- Series I: General Files, 1936-1961
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I includes Forge's personal and official correspondence, TWU Executive Board minutes, trial transcripts, leaflets and ATD reports. Documents reflect Forge's activity in the TWU, especially from the late 1940s, when he came into conflict with TWU officials. Also in this series are materials reflecting Forge's involvement in the creation and development of the ATD and CATA. Correspondence includes letters to his wife, Bess, letters from TWU president Michael Quill and former TWU official John Santo after Santo's deportation to Hungary for being a non-citizen Communist Party activist; and letters with Charles Smolikoff, Armand Scala, and Fred Swick of the TWU about the progress of forming the ATD. Also included is a 1947 transcript of Santo's Department of Immigration trial, as well as a transcript of 1950 proceedings against Forge by the TWU.
  - Administration: Executive Board members and correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution, 1937, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administration: Fordham Bus Company Administration: Fordham Bus Company, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Arthur S. Meyer to John Santo, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: M.F. to Bess Forge, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Charges against John Santo (1), Oct 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charges against John Santo (2), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statement by John Santo, ca.1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Administration: Minutes of the International Executive Board Meeting, Sep 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Air Transport Division: Arbitration Dispute with Pan American Airways, Inc., May 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Air Transport Division: Statements from ATD, Flight Safety, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence - Charles Smolikoff, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - International Executive Board Meeting (1), Nov 1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - International Executive Board Meeting (2), Nov 1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sixth Biennial Convention, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Air Transport Division: Administration, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Air Transport Division: Committee for Air Transport Autonomy, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Air Transport Division: Arbitration with American Airlines (1), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Air Transport Division: Arbitration with American Airlines (2), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Charles Smolikoff, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Proceedings of Airline Conference, Dec 1948 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Local 252, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - International Executive Board Meeting TWU Local 252, May 1949 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Air Transport Division: Administration, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Air Transport Division: Committee for Air Transport Autonomy, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Charles Smolikoff, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Armand Scala, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: Fred Swick, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - TWO Local 252, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Personal; March of Labor, Inc., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Charges against M.F., Mar 1950 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Airline Division: Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Charles Smolikoff, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Armand Scala, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Air Transport Division: Fred Swick, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - TWU Local 252, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - TWU Local 100, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence; Fred Swick, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Air Transport Division: Fred Swick, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - TWU Local 252, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Personal: Religion, Sacraments, ca.1952 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence; labor dispute of Pan American Airlines mechanics, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Fred Swick, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - TWU Local 252, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence Fred Swick, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Personal: Correspondence: Crestwood Bus Service, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Fred Swick, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence: John Santo and Michael Quill, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Air Transport Division: Fred Swick, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence; M.L. Edwards to B.H. Diesen, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Fred Swick, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - TWU Local 252 Agreement, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Fred Swick, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Air Transport Division: Flight Engineer Dispute, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Fred Swick, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Air Transport Division: Correspondence: Fred Swick, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Air Transport Division and Dave Lippert, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - TWU Local 252, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Series II: Clippings, Credentials, Flyers, Pamphlets, Photographs, 1937-1986
  Series II includes clippings on TWU leaders and labor issues; flyers publicizing union activities; and pamphlets by and about the TWU and the ATD. Other materials include publicity by the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) directed at TWU members and other government anti-Communist publications; a pamphlet, " How the Milwaukee Sentinel Exposed Milwaukee Communists"; and a HUAC publication of John Santo's trial transcript. Also in this series are photocopied clippings of editorials written by Forge in the 1970s and 1980s, a file of Forge's credentials and identification cards, and photographs.
  - Clippings: TWU, 1937-1951 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Clippings: Communism within TWU, 1937-1954 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Clippings: TWU Local 252 and bus strikes, 1939-1954 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Clippings: Michael Quill, 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Clippings: John Santo, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Clippings: M.F. Editorials, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Credentials and invitation cards, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Flyers: TWU, 1942-1955 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Pamphlets: TWU, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Pamphlets: "How the Milwaukee Sentinel Exposed Milwaukee Communists", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Pamphlets: Anti-Communist, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Pamphlets: HUAC, John Santo testimony, Mar 1963 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Photographs, circa 1934-1948 (Box 1, Folder 84)